Richard Koppe Papers
Richard Koppe Papers
1939-1963
Koppe, Richard.
0.5 linear ft.
American painter, sculptor. Born 1916.
Correspondence, incoming and outgoing (1948-1963); itineraries and exhibition lists, and other business related material; manuscripts, including essays and short stories; photographs; and published material.
149111
Biographical History
Educator, painter, and sculptor Richard Koppe was born in St. Paul, Minnesota on March 4, 1916. He studied at the St. Paul School of Art with Cameron Booth, LeRoy Turner and Nicoli Cikovsky. He also attended the New Bauhaus in Chicago, Illinois with Kepes and Archipenko. He has received prizes from the Art Institute of Chicago in 1947, 1948, 1950, and 1960, and from the San Francisco Art Association (1948).
Mr. Koppe is a modern artist who is quite well known for his abstract painting. Some of his best paintings are the "Bejeweled Bird," and "Reflection." Mr. Koppe's work may be seen at the Smith College Museum, the Whitney Museum of American Art, the Art Institute of Chicago, Syracuse University, and the Brooklyn Museum.
He has exhibited at nearly every major museum in the United States, including the Art Institute of Chicago, the Carnegie Institute, the Museum of Modern Art, the Whitney Museum of American Art, the Pennsylvania Academy of Fine Arts, the Corcoran Gallery of art and the Artists' Gallery in New York City.
Mr. Koppe was a professor at the Illinois Institute of Technology for nineteen years. In 1963 he became professor of Art at the University of Illinois in Chicago.
Scope and Contents of the Collection
The Richard Koppe Papers consist of six parts. Incoming correspondence is correspondence received by Richard Koppe. lt is divided into two groups, business and personal. Outgoing correspondence consists of correspondence written by Richard. The Subject files include itinerary and exhibition lists, receipts, statements, awards, and comments from exhibitors. Manuscripts consists of a further description of Koppe's work, several short stories by Koppe, and several essays by Koppe, all typescript. Photographs include photographs of Richard Koppe's works. Published material contains newspaper articles and press releases about Richard Koppe.
Arrangement of the Collection
Incoming correspondence is subdivided into business and personal, and each group is arranged alphabetically according to the name of the sender. Outgoing correspondence is arranged in chronological order. Subject files are arranged in alphabetical order by physical type. Manuscripts are grouped by type (essays, short stories) and are in alphabetical order by title. Photographs are arranged in alphabetical order according to the title of the work. Published material includes newspaper articles first, followed by press releases.
Subject and Genre Headings
Art -- Painters; Koppe, Richard.; Art, American -- 20th century.; Painters -- United States.; Painting, American-- 20th century.; Sculptors -- United States.; Sculpture, American -- 20th century.; Correspondence.; Essays.; Photographs.; Press releases.; Artists.; Painters.; Sculptors.
Access Restrictions
The majority of our archival and manuscript collections are housed offsite and require advanced notice for retrieval. Researchers are encouraged to contact us in advance concerning the collection material they wish to access for their research.
Inventory
- Incoming correspondence
  - Business correspondence
    - A-B (Box 1)
    - C-H (Box 1)
    - I-P (Box 1)
    - R-W (Box 1)
  - Personal correspondence
    - B-S (Box 1)
- Outgoing correspondence
  - February 1948-December 1953 (Box 1)
  - January 1954-July 1963 (Box 1)
  - Undated (Box 1)
- Subject files
  - Comments from exhibitors (Box 1)
  - Hallmark Art Award, 1949 (Box 1)
  - Itinerary and exhibition list (Box 1)
  - Measurements (Box 1)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 1)
  - Receipts (Box 1)
  - Statements (Box 1)
- Manuscripts
  - Further description of Koppe's work (Box 1)
  - Essays
    - "Sculpture", typescript (Box 1)
    - "Sources of Contemporary Painting", typescript (Box 1)
  - Short stories
    - "Gay Christmas", typescript (Box 1)
    - "Mirror for Man", typescript (Box 1)
- Photographs
  - "Bejeweled Bird", 1951 (Box 1)
  - "Charred Seraph", 1959 (Box 1)
  - "Curved Abstraction", 1945 (Box 1)
  - "Mystery", 1960-1961 (Box 1)
  - "Reflection", 1954 (Box 1)
  - "Reclining Figure", 1939 (Box 1)
  - "Seated Figure", 1939 (Box 1)
  - "Terrestrial", undated (Box 1)
  - "Trio", 1956 (Box 1)
  - "Two Totems", 1951 (Box 1)
  - Richard Koppe, undated (Box 1)
  - "Visage", undated (Box 1)
  - "Well of the Sea", 1948 (Box 1)
- Published material
  - Newspaper article about Koppe (Box 1)
  - Press Releases (Box 1)